Indiana University Undergraduate Library Services records, 1952-1998 C438
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University Undergraduate Library Services records
1952-1998
1970-1990
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University, Bloomington. Undergraduate Library Services
C438
5.8 cubic feet 7 boxes
Established in 1962, Indiana University's Undergraduate Library (UGL) was intended to offer more relevant services to IU's undergraduate students than what was being provided by the Main Library. Having officially changed its name to Undergraduate Library Services (UGLS), the department is extant today and is still offering many of the resources it once did in its early years, such as a browsing collection, a Media Center, and a career references section. This collection consists of a variety of records that pertain to the history and administration of UGLS, such as statistics, financial documents, policies, building maintenance and renovation. The collection also contains information on student-related activities and programs hosted by UGLS.
Access Restrictions
Select files closed to researchers. These are indicated in the folder list.
Advance notice required for access to collection.
Administrative History
First established in 1962, Indiana University's Undergraduate Library (UGL) was founded with the intention of providing undergraduate students with resources and programs more suitable to their needs than what was being offered by IU's Main Library. From 1962 to 1969, UGL contained between 33,000 and 65,000 books and periodicals, occupied three floors of space and was housed in what is today known as Joseph A. Franklin Hall. In 1969, UGL was moved to its present-day location in the west tower of the Herman B Wells Library.
Proud of its brightly-lit reading areas, reserve reading rooms and media materials, UGL also became known for its Media Center, its career reference and browsing collections, as well as the Resource Center for the Visually Impaired. Additionally, UGL played a key role in developing an innovative bibliographic instruction program for IU in the 1970s.
As a result of its merger with the Halls of Residence Libraries (HRL), the Undergraduate Library changed its official title in 1982, becoming the Undergraduate Library Services Department (UGLS). In more recent history, UGLS has been partnered with the Information Commons (IC), and is still committed to providing quality resources, support and information to undergraduate students at Indiana University.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into two series: Administrative files and Historic and subject files.
Scope and Content Note
The Undergraduate Library Services collection consists of 4.8 cubic feet of records that have been organized into two series: Administrative files and Historic and subject files. Files are arranged in alphabetical order within each series.
The Historic and subject files series contains 107 folders which span the years 1952 to 1996. Within this series there are several files regarding the development of the Undergraduate Library (UGL), both physically and administratively. There are, for example, blueprints, floor plans, correspondence and other documents which discuss possible renovations for UGL. There are also records that discuss issues, patron complaints, and potential improvements related to the UGL collection and services, or to the Halls of Residence Libraries (HRL). Also in the historic and subject series are files with information about programs hosted by UGL for students and their parents, such as library tours, term paper workshops, Independent learning programs, etc. One folder from this series ("Incident Reports, 1983-1989") has been restricted.
The Administrative files series spans the period from 1962 to 1998 and contains a wide range of topics from dissertation policies to equipment requests. The majority of these files are statistics or financial documents like budget reports, equipment requests, user/book counts, etc. One of the more unique folders in this series is the "UGLS Endowment, 1988-1990" file. This file contains programs and email correspondence about the Bob Knight Library Endowment which, with the help of Bob Knight, attempted to raise $300,000 for the Indiana University Bloomington Libraries over a three year period. Fourteen photographs, the majority of which are of IU sports coaches, have been transferred to the photograph collection. However, photocopies remain within the original file.
Acquisition Information
Accession Numbers: 2011/026, 96/040
Provenance
This collection was transferred to the University Archives from librarian Lou Malcomb in March of 2011.
Appraisal
Weekly and monthly statistics, blank forms, duplicate forms, and desk schedules have been removed and discarded.
Undergraduate libraries --Indiana --Bloomington.; Indiana University. Undergraduate Library Services; Indiana University, Bloomington. Undergraduate Library Services -- Archives; Indiana University, Bloomington. Undergraduate Library Services -- Records and correspondence; Indiana University. Undergraduate Library Services -- Archives; Indiana University. Undergraduate Library Services -- Records and correspondence
- Historic and subject files, 1952-1996 (Box 1)
  - Athletics Program, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
  - Books remaining after the 1969 fire (Box 1)
  - Business/School of Public and Environmental Affairs (SPEA), 1995 (Box 1)
  - Circulation manual for desk workers, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Children's Collection, 1980-1984 (Box 1)
  - Collection Development Lists Used in Forming UGL, 1962-1977 (Box 1)
  - Collection Review, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Computer Cluster 24-Hr, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Custodial Services, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Early Registration Activities, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Elevators, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Energy Crisis, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Freshman Orientation (Box 1)
    - 1982 (Box 1)
    - Fall 1983 (Box 1)
    - 1984 (Box 1)
    - Fall 1985 (Box 1)
  - Freshman Seminar, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Group Study in UGL, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Halls of Residence Libraries (Box 1)
    - Halls of Residence Libraries, 1979-1987 (Box 1)
    - Budget, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Catalog, 1993-1994 (Box 1)
    - Changes, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - Collins Move, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - Display Areas, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Follow-up, 1988-1990 (Box 1)
    - Issues, 1977-1992 (Box 1)
      General
      (2 files)
    - Teter Library Renovation, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Teter Open House, Fall 1983 (Box 1)
    - Thefts and Vandalism, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Honors Program, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Improvements, 1985-1988 (Box 1)
  - Incident Reports, 1983-1989 (Box 1)
    RESTRICTED
  - Incidents Involving Patrons (not Noise) (Box 1)
    - 1979-1984 (Box 1)
    - 1988-1991 (Box 1)
  - Incidents Involving Staff and Patrons, 1981-1984 (Box 1)
  - Independent Learning Program, 1971-1973 (Box 1)
  - Indiana Daily Student- Arrest of 2 Students in Library, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Ins and Outs, 1988-1990 (Box 1)
  - IU Libraries Graduate Student Organization, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - IU Regional Campuses, 1985-1990 (Box 1)
  - Keys, 1975-1983 (Box 1)
  - Library Hours, 1984-1985 (Box 1)
  - Library Instruction Room (Box 1)
    - Renovation, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
    - Room Use Guidelines, 1984-1985 (Box 1)
  - Library Security Policy, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Lights, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Lost and Found, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Meetings and Reports, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Mini University, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - New Library Information, undated (Box 1)
  - Parents Day, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Patron Complaints, 1985-1987 (Box 1)
  - Patron Property Damage, 1982-1985 (Box 1)
  - Physical Condition of UGL, 1978-1982 (Box 1)
  - Policies- Historical, 1963-1967 (Box 1)
  - Reference Assistants (Box 1)
    - Reference Assistants, 1980-1986 (Box 1)
    - Combination Issues, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
    - Desk/Counter, 1983-1985 (Box 1)
    - Evaluation Survey, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Issues, 1989-1991 (Box 1)
    - Material, 1972-1977 (Box 1)
  - Repairs/Maintanence, 1981-1985 (Box 1)
  - Reserves (Box 1)
    - Reserves, 1983-1986 (Box 1)
    - Arbutus on Reserves, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Automation Project, 1972-1974 (Box 1)
    - Book Operations- Other Libraries, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - Brainstorming- General, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Branch Reserves, 1982-1987 (Box 2)
    - Circulation Statistics, 1981-1985 (Box 2)
    - Combination Graduate and Undergraduate, 1973-1981 (Box 2)
    - Complaints and Correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box 2)
    - Factsheet, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - Fines, 1983 (Box 2)
    - In IO, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Issues, 1980-1989 (Box 2)
    - Issues History, 1964-1978 (Box 2)
    - McBee Cards, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Material for Readers for the Blind, 1985 (Box 2)
    - Materials Task Force, 1982 (Box 2)
    - Policies and Procedures, 1983-1984 (Box 2)
    - Policy Statement, 1973-1978 (Box 2)
    - Space Needs, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Study, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Tapes, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Task Force, 1968-1981 (Box 2)
    - Transfer, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Secure Area, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Shelving (Box 2)
    - Manual, 1985 (Box 2)
    - UGL, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Stacks- UGL, 1984-19859 (Box 2)
  - Student Building and UGL Plans, Maps, etc., 1961 (Box 2)
  - Student Government Issues, 1989-1992 (Box 2)
  - Summer Programs' Liaison Role, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Temperature/Humidity, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Term Paper Workshop, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Test File, 1977-1983 (Box 2)
  - Theft and Vandalism, 1980-1985 (Box 2)
  - Tour Outlines, 1982-1990 (Box 2)
  - 24-Hour Study Room (Box 2)
    - 1975-1985 (Box 2)
    - Space Count, 1983-1985 (Box 2)
  - Undergraduate Library (UGL) (Box 2)
    - General History, 1952-1968 (Box 2)
    - 1965-1986 (Box 2)
    - Blueprints and Floor plans, 1961 (Box 2)
    - Carpet Replacement, 1983-1984 (Box 2)
    - Floor plans, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Floor plans- Public Display, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Librarians, 1966-1971 (Box 2)
    - Publicity, 1973-1977 (Box 2)
    - Univ. of Maryland, 1973 (Box 2)
- Administrative files, 1962-1998
  - American Library Association (ALA)- Library Instruction in Acadmic Libraries, after 1985 (Box 2)
  - Art Books in UGL, 1980-1982 (Box 2)
  - Baatz Notes, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Bob Knight Requests, 1993-1995 (Box 2)
  - Books (Box 2)
    - Budget, 1964-1973 (Box 2)
    - Prices, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Branch Library Manual, 1983-1993 (Box 2)
  - Browsing Collection, 1973-1990 (Box 2)
  - Budget (Box 2)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 2)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 2)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 2)
    - Cuts, 1987-1991 (Box 2)
    - Requests, 1974-1980 (Box 2)
      (3 files)
    - Request- IU Quality Improvement, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Request- $250,000, 1992-1993 (Box 2)
    - Hourly, 1977-1986 (Box 2)
      (5 files)
    - Hourly Accounts, 1985-1986 (Box 2)
    - Materials Budget, 1982-1997 (Box 2A)
      (6 files)
    - Materials Budget Request, 1986-1990 (Box 2A)
      (4 files)
    - Materials Budget Request for UGL and Media, 1983-1988 (Box 2A)
    - Midyear Materials Budget Allocation Request for UGL and Media, 1984-1985 (Box 2A)
    - Midyear Materials Budget Request for UGL and Media, 1983-1984 (Box 2A)
    - Personnel, 1982 (Box 2A)
    - Requests and Purchases, 1989-1990 (Box 2A)
    - Serials Fund, 1977-1978 (Box 2A)
  - Bulletin Cases, 1988-1990 (Box 2A)
  - Central Circulation Services for Discussion/Resolution, 1985-1989 (Box 2A)
  - Children's Collection, 1971-1985 (Box 2A)
  - Circulation Policy Task Force, 1983-1992 (Box 3)
  - Collection Analysis, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Collection Development, 1982-1983 (Box 3)
  - College catalogs, 1978-1984 (Box 3)
  - Committee on Institutional Cooperation (CIC), 1990 (Box 3)
  - Copy Machines, 1975-1986 (Box 3)
  - Dean's Planning Session, 1990 (Box 3)
  - Dissertation Policies, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Equipment (Box 3)
    - Budget, 1980-1982 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1985 (Box 3)
    - Requests, 1962-1993 (Box 3)
  - Faculty Seminars, 1985-1993 (Box 3)
  - Family Student Housing, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Food and Drink, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Freshman Flyer, 1988 (Box 3)
  - Frontlog, 1988-1991 (Box 3)
  - Furnishings, 1973-1986 (Box 3)
  - Furniture, 1984-1985 (Box 3)
  - Guidelines for Planning and Development, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Instruction in Use of Library Slide Project (Box 3)
    - 1971-1976 (Box 3)
    - Issues, 1984-1992 (Box 3)
    - Programs, 1981-1987 (Box 3)
  - IU Bulletins- Library Section, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - Inventory, 1976-1982 (Box 3)
  - Inventory procedures, 1979-1985 (Box 3)
  - Libraries Mission Statement, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Library (Box 3)
    - Hours- Comparison, 1990-1991 (Box 3)
    - Instruction Projects, 1973-1977 (Box 3)
    - Instruction Task Force, 1985 (Box 3)
    - Terminal Cluster (Bloomington Academic Computing), 1982-1984 (Box 3)
    - Information Service Proposal, 1988 (Box 3)
  - Loan Policies (Box 3)
    - 1973-1991 (Box 3)
    - Committee, 1971-1981 (Box 3)
  - LTRES proposal, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Lunch Utilizing Video (LUV), 1982 (Box 3)
  - Machine Manuals, 1965-1973 (Box 3)
  - Malaysia, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - Masterheads/Factsheets, etc., 1983 (Box 3)
  - Media Center- Plans for Autonomy, 1985 (Box 3)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) Requests, 1991-1995 (Box 3)
  - Peer Institution Collection Development Survey, Spring 1983 (Box 3)
  - Renovation (Box 3)
    - Main Library Addition, 1987-1993 (Box 3)
    - Planning, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
    - Plans, 1983-1992 (Box 4)
    - Task Force, 1984-1985 (Box 4)
  - Reports, Annual, 1963-1998 (Box 4)
    (23 folders)
  - Serials (Box 4)
    - Department procedures, 1982-1985 (Box 4)
    - Management Data Fund 68, 1982-1984 (Box 4)
    - Management Data Fund 97, 1982-1984 (Box 4)
    - On microfilm backfile, 1987-1992 (Box 4)
    - Project, 1977-1980 (Box 4)
    - Review and cancellations, 1987 (Box 4)
    - Summary, 1983-1984 (Box 4)
    - UGL Procedures, 1984 (Box 4)
  - Staff Meetings, 1982-1991 (Box 5)
  - Statistics (Box 5)
    - 1978-1995 (Box 5)
      (8 files)
    - ARL, 1979-1992 (Box 5)
      (7 files)
    - Book Count, 1962-1972 (Box 5)
    - Collection Development, 1979-1982 (Box 5)
    - Circulation and Reserve Operations, 1974-1977 (Box 5)
    - Instructions, Association of Research Libraries (ARL), 1990-1991 (Box 5)
    - Order, 1966-1969 (Box 5)
    - Reference Desk, 1995-1996 (Box 5)
    - UGL, 1968-1994 (Box 5)
    - UGL, 1984-1997 (Box 5)
      (9 files)
  - Strategic Plan- IU Libraries, 1988 (Box 5)
  - UGL Collection Development (Box 5)
    - Materials Budget, 1968-1981 (Box 5)
    - Collection Review, 1992-1994 (Box 5)
    - Review and Reorganization, 1971-1972 (Box 5)
  - UGLS (Box 5)
    - Circulation, 1991-1992 (Box 5)
    - Endowment, 1988-1990 (Box 5)
    - Newsletter, 1989-1991 (Box 5)
  - Use Counts (Body Counts) (Box 5)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 5)
    - Study, 1980-1985 (Box 5)
  - User Surveys (Box 5)
    - 1983 (Box 5)
    - (Bus/Spea, UGLS, RC), 1983-1987 (Box 5)
  - Videotaping in the Library- Notes, Policies, etc., 1987 (Box 5)
  - Walden University Report, 1995 (Box 5)
  - Weeding, 1982-1991 (Box 6)
  - Workshop for Student Library Assistants (Box 6)
    - General File, 1955-1964 (Box 6)
    - Counselor's Handbooks, 1959-1964 (Box 6)
    - "The Workshop for Student Library Assistants: An Evaluation", 1955 (Box 6)
  - RESTRICTED FILE (Box 6)